A Guide to the William Harry Clarke Collection, 1935-1946
West Virginia State Archives
West Virginia State Archives
William Harry Clarke Collection, 1935-1946
West Virginia State Archives, Charleston, West Virginia
Ms2021-207
3 boxes
William Harry Clarke, Jr and Ruth Gilmore Clarke
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Custodial History
The entirety of this collection was donated by William Harry Clarke III, the son of Chaplain William Harry Clarke and Ruth Clarke. It was acquired by the West Virginia Archives and History in June of 2021.
Biographical/Historical Note
William Harry Clarke, Jr. was born in Huntington, West Virginia, in March of 1913. He and his wife, Ruth Gilmore, born in 1914, met as teenagers at Temple Baptist Church, while attending high school together at Huntington High School. Both graduated from Marshall College.
A vast majority of these letters were written during the time of World War II when Clarke resigned from pastoring at the Highland Park Baptist Church to serve with the 9th Army in England, France, and Germany. William Harry Clarke, Jr. and Ruth Gilmore Clarke had a son named William Harry Clarke III also known as "Sonny." Ruth and Sonny visited the Chaplain during his schooling at Harvard until he was shipped overseas. As a result, they moved to Portsmouth, Virginia to be with Ruth's parents while Chaplain Clarke served out his time with the military. Some of the letters are written from Huntington.
Scope and Content
This collection includes correspondence between Chaplain William Harry Clarke to his wife and son Ruth and William Harry Clarke III (Sonny). The correspondence occurred during World War II with Chaplain Clarke being stationed overseas in various places ranging from Paris to Berlin, while the family was in the United States. In addition, there are miscellaneous items, religious pamphlets, associated photographs, drawings by "Sonny," etc. The main components of this collection are:
Correspondence between Chaplain William Harry Clarke and Ruth Clarke, his wife (1935-1946).
Correspondence between Chaplain William Harry Clarke and William Harry Clarke III (Sonny), his son.
Miscellaneous correspondence sent to Chaplain William Harry Clarke.
Photographs of his wife and son, and military exploits while in the service and overseas.
Miscellaneous newspaper clippings.
Scenes from post-war Germany (or Europe).
Transferred to Museums
Framed Portrait, William Henry Clarke
Framed Portrait, William Harry Clarke
Swastika armband
Upholstery from chair of Herman Goering, Berchtesgaden, June 1945
Dogtags, patches, and military insignia
Chaplain's flag, which flew from jeep in Europe, 1945-1946
Contents List
- Box 1
  - Correspondence, William Harry Clarke to Ruth Gilmore, 1935 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Correspondence, William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, 1937 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to William Harry Clarke, 1937 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, June 1944 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, July 1944 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, November 1944 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, December 1944 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, January 1945 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, February 1945 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, March 1945 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, April 1945 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, May 1945 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, June 1945 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, July 1945 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, August 1945 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, September 1945 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, October 1945 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, November 1945 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, December 1945 (Box-folder 1:19)
- Box 2
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, January 1946 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, February 1946 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, March 1946 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, April 1946 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, May 1946 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, June 1946 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, July 1946 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Correspondence, Ruth Clarke to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, August 1946 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, June 1944 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, July 1944 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, November 1944 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, December 1944 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, January 1945 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, February 1945 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, March 1945 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, April 1945 (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, May 1945 (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, June 1945 (Box-folder 2:18)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, July 1945 (Box-folder 2:19)
- Box 3
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, August 1945 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, September 1945 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, October 1945 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, November 1945 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, December 1945 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, January 1946 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, February 1946 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, March 1946 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, April 1946 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, May 1946 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, June 1946 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Ruth Clarke, July 1946 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Correspondence to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Correspondence, Rene Robinson to Ruth Clarke, December 1944 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Correspondence, telegrams from William Harry Clarke (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Correspondence, regarding retrieval of historical paintings, St. Ulrich Lutheran Church, Augsburg, Germany, June 21, 1945 (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Correspondence to Ruth and Sonny Clarke (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Correspondence, Grandmother to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, 1945 (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Correspondence, Mother to Chaplain William Harry Clarke, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 3:19)
  - Correspondence, Chaplain William Harry Clarke to Sonny Clarke, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Correspondence, miscellaneous V-Mail (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Chaplain William Harry Clarke, Diary/Planner, 1945 (Box-folder 3:22)
  - Chaplain William Harry Clarke, Diary/Planner, 1946 (Box-folder 3:23)
  - Chaplain William Harry Clarke, Meal Card, Transatlantic Crossing, December 1946 (Box-folder 3:24)
  - Chaplain William Harry Clarke, Military Papers, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 3:25)
  - Documents, religious services, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 3:26)
  - Stars and Stripes, 1945 (Box-folder 3:27)
  - Newsletter, Lincoln Junior High School, Huntington, January 1929 (Box-folder 3:28)
  - William Harry Clarke, certificates of completion, training courses for Sunday School workers, April 22, 1938 (Box-folder 3:29)
  - Correspondence, William Harry Clarke and President Lyndon Johnson, 1964 (Box-folder 3:30)
  - Correspondence, Bill Moyers to Harry Clarke, September 24, 1966 (Box-folder 3:31)
  - Autobiographical information, William Harry Clarke, 1999 (Box-folder 3:32)
  - Clippings (Box-folder 3:33)